<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defence of the liturgy of the Church of England being an answer to the book of divers ministers of sundry counties, entituled, reasons shewing the necessity of reformation of the publick doctrine and worship &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82275</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868879</idno>
  <idno type="VID">121235</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240954941</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D817</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E2106_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210045</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868879</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99868879e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82275)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121235)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 241:E2106[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defence of the liturgy of the Church of England being an answer to the book of divers ministers of sundry counties, entituled, reasons shewing the necessity of reformation of the publick doctrine and worship &amp;c.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 79, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T. Garthwait at the little North-door of St. Pauls Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Burges, Cornelius.  Reasons shewing the necessity of reformation of the publick 1. doctrine, 2. worship, 3. rites and ceremonies, 4. church-government, and discipline, reputed to be (but indeed, not) established by law.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Burges, Cornelius, 1589?-1665. --  Reasons shewing the necessity of reformation of the publick 1. doctrine, 2. worship, 3. rites and ceremonies, 4. church-government, and discipline, reputed to be (but indeed, not) established by law.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">Church of England --  Liturgy --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121235:1"/>
            <p>A DEFENCE OF THE LITURGY OF THE Church of ENGLAND</p>
            <p>Being An Answer to the Book of Divers Ministers of sundry Counties, Entituled, <hi>Reasons shewing the Necessity of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the publick Doctrine and worship</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. Garthwait</hi> at the Little North-door of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church. 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:121235:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:121235:2"/>
            <head>The most learned Dr. <hi>SANDERSON</hi> hath this passage in his <hi>Preface</hi> to his Sermons Sect. 23.</head>
            <p>THe Reverend Arch-Bishop <hi>Whitgift,</hi> and the learned <hi>Hooker,</hi> men of great <hi>judgement,</hi> and <hi>famous</hi> in their times, did long since <hi>foresee,</hi> and accordingly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared their fear, that if ever <hi>Puritanism</hi> should prevail among us, it would soon draw in <hi>Anabaptism</hi> after it. At this <hi>Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright</hi> and other the advocates for the <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplinarian</hi> interest in those dayes, seemed to take <hi>great offence:</hi> as if those <hi>fears</hi> were rather <hi>pretended</hi> to derive an <hi>odium</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, then that there was otherwise any <hi>just cause</hi> for the same; protesting ever their utter dislike of <hi>Anabaptism,</hi> and how free they were from the least thought of introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing it. But this was onely their own mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stake; or rather Jealousie. For those <hi>god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men</hi> were neither so unadvised, nor so uncharitable, as to become Judges of other mens thoughts or intentions, beyond what their actions spoke them. They onely consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as <hi>prudent</hi> men, that <hi>Anabaptisme</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:121235:3"/>had its <hi>rise,</hi> from the same <hi>Principles</hi> the <hi>Puritans</hi> held; and its <hi>growth,</hi> from the same <hi>courses</hi> they <hi>took,</hi> together with the natural tendency of those <hi>principles</hi> and <hi>practises</hi> thitherward; especially of that <hi>one principle,</hi> as it was by them mis-under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood, that the <hi>Scripture</hi> was <hi>adaequata a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendorum regula,</hi> so as nothing might be <hi>lawfully done</hi> without express <hi>warrant</hi> either from some <hi>command,</hi> or <hi>example</hi> therein contained. <hi>The clue</hi> whereof, if followed on as far as it would lead, would certainly in time carry them as far as the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> were then gone. But that it was no <hi>vain fear,</hi> the unhappy <hi>event</hi> hath proved; and <hi>justified</hi> them: since what they feared is now <hi>come to pass,</hi> and that in a very high degree. Yet did not they see <hi>the threed</hi> drawn out to that <hi>length,</hi> as we have seen it; (the name of <hi>Quakers, See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, &amp;c.</hi> not then heard of in the world:) but how much <hi>farther</hi> it will reach none can say; for no man yet ever saw the bottom of <hi>the clue:</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121235:3"/>
            <head>A DEFENCE OF THE LITURGY OF THE CHURCH of ENGLAND, Against The accusations of it contain'd in a Book intituled, <hi>Reasons shewing the necessity of Reformation of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick.</hi> 1. <hi>Doctrine.</hi> 2. <hi>Worship.</hi> 3. <hi>Rites and Ceremonies.</hi> 4. <hi>Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Discipline,</hi> offered to the present Parliament by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Ministers of sundry Counties in <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His undertaking intends only the satisfaction of the Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans conscience: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it meddles not with the objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which the forementioned Book
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:121235:4"/>produceth against the <hi>Articles</hi> of Doctrine, or against the Church-Government. For the exceptions against the former, all save one [which I shall answer immediately,] do only insist upon the inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which the subscription to the Book of <hi>Articles</hi> is said to bring up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Ministers; or upon the defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiveness of those Articles to be sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed by a Synod: and though all, that is there said against the Church-Government, were true; yet the common People might lawfully sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to it, commanding lawful things. The Ministers of <hi>England</hi> therefore being supposed able to satisfie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in that, which concerns them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; or at least better then I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume to do: I shall only justifie the LITURGY, in which the meanest people being Actors, they must needs become guilty, when they worship God after that form; if it were as bad, as the Petitioners would make it.</p>
            <div type="objection">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:121235:4"/>
               <head>OBJECTION.</head>
               <p>The only Objection against the Articles, which comes in the way of my designe to answer, is in these words, Pag. 3. §. 5. <hi>That all being by Artic.</hi> 35. <hi>to admit both books of Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies to contain a godly and wholsome Doctrine necessary for these times; men must subscribe to false Doctrines and Assertions.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>IT follows not. For the Homilies may contain Godly and wholsome Doctrines, though there be false as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sertions intermixed, especially if they be not ungodly and unwhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some: and he that subscribes to the former, doth not to the latter. For it is not said in the Article, that they contain nothing but godly and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some Doctrine; and the subscriber
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:121235:5"/>to the Article subscribes to no more then is said in the Article. He that saith, he believes the works of Saint <hi>Austin</hi> do contain a godly and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some Doctrine; doth not by those words subscribe to every mistake, that is found in his works: neither doth he, who saith, I believe that the Sermons made by Ministers of our Times contain a godly and wholsome doctrine, by these words subscribe to the errours, the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, the slips of tongue, which the Authors themselves must confess do sometimes fall out in their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, except they are infallible. As for the two instances, which the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners give, I can see no false Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in either of them. The first is this, <hi>One of the Homilies saith, that Plurality of wifes was by special pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative suffered to the Fathers of the Old Testament, not for satisfaction of their carnal and fleshly lusts, but to have many children: because every
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121235:5"/>one of them hoped and begged of God in their Prayers, that that blessed seed, which God promised should come into the world to break the Serpents head, might be born of his stock and kindred.</hi> All they have to say against this clause is only this. <hi>As if all did not knew out of what tribe Christ was to issue.</hi> But I answer, (1.) Here is no argument in this, except it be a false doctrine to assert, that all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Old Testament knew not out of what tribe Christ was to issue. And if it be a false doctrine; it must also be proved to be so, before they can justly charge him that holds it, with subscribing to false doctrine. And when they have proved this, I can expect they should prove also the rest of that they have to say a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Liturgy, and not till then. (2.) Though it were granted, that<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after the forbidding of intermarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages among the tribes, any man, who was not of the tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:121235:6"/>might know, that Christ should not spring from him; until some cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity or other accident in the Nation might cause the breaking of that law, and the mixing of the Tribes, which well might be supposed probable in time to come: yet the Fathers of the Old Testament, before the division of the Tribes, could not possibly know, that Christ should not spring from them, although they knew he should be born of <hi>Judah.</hi> For <hi>Reuben</hi> might hope, that some of his posterity might match with the posterity of <hi>Judah.</hi> Much less could the Fathers know it, who dyed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Judah</hi> was born. And the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily doubtless intends them before <hi>Abraham;</hi> because they are said to expect Christ only under the notion of the <hi>womans seed,</hi> whereas after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he was expected more under the title of <hi>Abrahams seed.</hi> And so you see, here is no false doctrine proved in the first instance, but only
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:121235:6"/>boldly affirm'd. The second is this, <hi>That another Homily hath these words. [The same Lesson doth the Holy Ghost teach us in sundry places of the Scripture] for this is alledged,</hi> Tob. 4. verse 10 <hi>This expression doth evidently admit of these two gross Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.</hi> (1.) <hi>That the Book of</hi> Tobit <hi>is to be taken for holy Scripture.</hi> (2.) <hi>That it was endited by the Holy Ghost.</hi> I answer to the first, that Apocryphal books were by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients, and may be called Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures or writings, though not Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical; both because they treat of holy things, and are used in holy offices. To the second, that it doth not follow from the cited expression, that this book was endited by the Holy Ghost; but only that the pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage quoted out of this book is so. For if holy men by their lives are the Epistle of Christ, written by the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Christ; much more properly may their holy words be termed so.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121235:7"/>So that this phrase hath a tolerable sound; especially in the ear of those, who are wont to say touching assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that there is an inward voice of the spirit ordinarily spoken to the believers soul, which is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to be believed for its own evidence, as the Sun is seen by its own light, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reflection upon those ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal marks and signes, which distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish the voice of the true spirit from that of a false. But again, though the Homily saith the Holy Ghost teacheth us in sundry places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture such a Lesson, and afterward quotes a place out of <hi>Tobit;</hi> yet the Homily doth not say that the Holy Ghost doth teach it in that place. I confess the words are doubtful in their meaning; and he who takes them in the wrong meaning doth subscribe to a falsity: but the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners do not conclude only that a man <hi>may</hi> be in danger of it, but that a man <hi>must</hi> subscribe to a false asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:121235:7"/>in these words; which cannot be, unless he <hi>must</hi> needs take the words by the wrong handle; when they have a right one. Whereas it is lastly said, <hi>That though the Article tells us, that the Church doth not apply Apocryphals to establish Doctrine; this Homily applies these Apocryphal passages to confirm the Doctrine of Alms.</hi> I answer, every quoting of an Author to witness unto a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is not used for the <hi>establishment</hi> of it, as the word is intended to sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the binding of the Intellect to assent to it with a divine faith. For then the Apostle pins our faith upon <hi>Aratus</hi> his sleeve, when he quotes that sentence, <hi>For we are his off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spring.</hi> If they reply, but in the Homily under debate the verse is quoted as from the Holy Ghost; they do only recur back, and so should I, if I should answer them. There is no more needful to be said pertinently to my present designe,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:121235:8"/>upon this subject; but only to take notice, that what they say, <hi>Pag.</hi> 5. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst an enforced subscription to these Articles, doth hold as much against imposing the confession of faith, made by the Divines at <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster,</hi> as the test of Orthodoxisme. For it was not thought sufficient, that a man should assent to that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession with this Proviso, <hi>so far forth as it is agreeable to the word of God: by which,</hi> say the Petitioners, <hi>it must needs be granted that the composers of them are admitted infallible, and their articles of equal authority with Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Scripture.</hi> But then was then, and now is now.</p>
               <p>I proceed to what they say against the LITURGY. And first they call into question, whether it be the same intended in the Act of Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> But this is to question the Queens priviledge, by which it was set out. Again, whereas the Act saith there should be alterations made in it from
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121235:8"/>that set forth by King <hi>Edward</hi> only in two or three sentences; they mention many alterations, though not in sentences, but in the directory for reading the Scriptures. And to reckon up these alterations is the greatest part of their task. But if all they mention were true; he that reads the Act may satisfie himself, finding it provided toward the end, <hi>that the Queens Majesty with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Metropolitane might or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain and publish further Rites and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In that sheet inserted into their Book, they cry out against that <hi>Translation of the Psalms</hi> annexed to the Book of Common Prayer. But (1.) There is no command in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy to use that Translation, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then another. (2.) If there be any other injunction to read that Translation; it may be lawfully done, notwithstanding all the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours imputed to it. For when it is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121235:9"/>objected, <hi>How then is nothing read, but the pure word of God, or that which is grounded upon it, which is promised in the Preface?</hi> I answer, How would it be, if the Translation of King <hi>James</hi> were only read? It is usual for men, that bear no good will to the Common Prayer-Book, to give the sense of their Text quite contrary to the Import even of King <hi>James</hi> his Translation; and if so, the case of both these Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slations is alike for kind, and differs in degree only, themselves being Judges. I know an able Divine of the Independent way, who preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed several Sermons upon <hi>Zeph.</hi> 2.1. which he read, <hi>sift your selves,</hi> or, <hi>examine your selves;</hi> whereas the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Translation renders it, <hi>gather your selves together.</hi> Indeed they instance a plain contradiction betwixt the two Translations in <hi>Psalm</hi> 105.28. <hi>They were not obedient,</hi> saith one: <hi>they rebelled not,</hi> saith the other. But you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121235:9"/>may find just such another contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction betwixt the usual Translati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the Original, in <hi>Isa.</hi> 9.3. <hi>Thou hast not encreased the joy,</hi> saith one: <hi>thou hast encreased it,</hi> saith the other,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 20. They except against the reading of <hi>Tobit</hi> thus. <hi>In Tob. the third, where mention is made that</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah <hi>the daughter of</hi> Raguel <hi>had been married to seven husbands, whom</hi> Asmodeus <hi>the evil spirit had killed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they lay with her [a likely mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter!] yet was she reproached by her Fathers Maids for strangling them all.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:121235:10"/>
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>ANd why not a likely matter? Is such an interjection suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to confute an History, that commemorates extraordinary e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents? For there is nothing in the relation inconsistent with it self, to render it unworthy of an historical Faith. Again they go on in obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting against this Book, <hi>In Tob.</hi> 3. <hi>v. g. it is said, Alms doth deliver from death and shall purge away all sin. What need then the blood of Christ?</hi> I might as well reason thus, if <hi>Jacob</hi> got the blessing by his savoury meat; what need then his fathers good will? Or thus, such a man is indemnified by having no hand in the Kings death; what need then the Act of Pardon? The blood of Christ it self cannot deliver from death, but by alms; taking it for an inward propension to charitable
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:121235:10"/>actions. Again they have this note upon the same Chapter, <hi>One</hi> Rapha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el <hi>telleth</hi> Tobit <hi>thus, I am Raphael one of the seven holy Angels, which present the prayers of the Saints. Whereas none but Christ doth present their Prayers;</hi> which is clearly false, if <hi>[none]</hi> be understood of men as well as of Angels. For how many prayers of sick persons and others, are presented to God by the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation? Is not seconding a Petition presenting it! When the people pray for <hi>David,</hi> that God would fulfil all his Petitions; do not they present his Petitions to God, and make <hi>intercession</hi> for him, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> bids us to do it for Kings? But if they mean by <hi>[none]</hi> only <hi>no Angel;</hi> how doth it appear, that no Angel backs our Prayers? They put down, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.3. as if it were a proof. But I read nothing in that place, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that an Angel was seen presenting the prayers of the Saints to God.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121235:11"/>But what though one Angel did, doth it follow hence that another doth not? Suppose Christ were sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by that Angel in that vision; yet it doth not follow, that because he intercedes, therefore the Angels intercede not. Though he presents prayers; others may present them too, though not in the same man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; even as he is a Priest, and yet no body denies but that there are other Priests too, though not in the same sense. Though there be but one Mediatour by way of satisfaction to justice; yet it is manifest, that there are many by way of supplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to mercy. They go on, <hi>This</hi> Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phael <hi>was a lying either man or spirit, for he saith I am</hi> Azarias <hi>the son of</hi> Ananias. But I answer, the words signifie no more but this necessarily, I am in the shape of <hi>Azarias,</hi> or I go under the name of him, and am taken by every body for him, and I am no body but he. When St. <hi>John</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:121235:11"/>saw multitudes in white robes with Palms in their hands; no man can say, that the Elder lyed, who told him upon his question, these are they that came out of tribulation; because they were represented in that vision. And so also <hi>Raphael</hi> might say, he was <hi>Azarias,</hi> without a lye, whom he represented to <hi>Tobit</hi> in an apparition. But let it be never so gross a lye, it makes no more [ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken singly without other considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which the Petitioners urge not] against the use of that book; then that lye of <hi>Jacob, I am thy son Esau,</hi> makes against the book of <hi>Genesis.</hi> And the following passage of <hi>Judith</hi> is by themselves parallel'd with the act of <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levy:</hi> and when they read other books of Scripture, which relate the delusions of lying spirits, or the errours of men misled by a blind zeal of God; they may as well, upon the account of this reason alone, be said to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:121235:12"/>with Dunghills, as they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonably call this book for the bad things which it only makes an histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of. These evil pranks [as they call them] recorded both in Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical and Apocryphal books, are read in the Church for good ends. And if there were not good ends, even when the case seems to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved in the book; the Holy Ghost would not have left on record the treachery of <hi>Jael</hi> toward <hi>Sisera,</hi> and joyn to it the hymn of a Prophetess which seems to applaud it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION.</head>
               <p>Pag. 22. §. 1. <hi>They finde fault with the word Priest, because they finde it not the title of a Minister in the New Testament.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:121235:12"/>
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p n="1">(1.) NO more is either <hi>Minister</hi> or <hi>Presbyter,</hi> found in the new Testament <hi>appropriated</hi> to that office, which is styled in the Liturgy by the name of <hi>Priesthood.</hi> For we read of women beside Deacons, that are termed <hi>Ministers;</hi> and officers of the Synagogue and of civil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistories were termed <hi>Presbyters.</hi> (2.) Every Christian is termed Priest in the New Testament; and why may not a Minister? (3.) Why may not a Minister of Christ be called a <hi>Christian Priest,</hi> as well as the day of Christ be called the <hi>Christian Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath?</hi> Since both these names are Jewish in their extraction, and Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths are more plainly said to be done away then Priests; why should the latter be so violently contended against by those, which earnestly contend for the former? (4.) Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:121235:13"/>of the Gospel are called Priests in Old Testament-prophecies of New Testament-times. (5.) The English word <hi>[Priest]</hi> is thought by learned men to be derived from <hi>[Prester]</hi> a diminutive of <hi>[Presbyter;]</hi> for <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter Johannes</hi> is the same with <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster John.</hi> And therefore seeing it signifies a <hi>Presbyter;</hi> they should rather finde fault with the Transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours for giving this name to those, that ministred at the Jewish Altar, whom the French Translation calls <hi>Sacrisicateurs,</hi> then with the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy for giving it to Christian Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, to whom properly it belongs. And as for the Greek and Latine words, which are turned <hi>Priest;</hi> they signifie only one, that hath to do in holy things. Now whereas they object, that this word doth connote a sacrifice: they cannot be ignorant, that the Ministers of the Gospel have as much sacrifice as <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> had, the Priest of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:121235:13"/>most high God, <hi>viz.</hi> Blessings, bread and wine, the sacrifice of praise, or the calvs of their lips. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that which they say next, is a mere sophisme, if not an industrious one. For having premised, <hi>that this title is no way warranted by the word of God in the Pontisician sense;</hi> they assume, <hi>yet it is used above fifty times in our Liturgy.</hi> But they cunningly leave out that clause <hi>in the Pontifician sense.</hi> Therefore that their syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gisme may proceed according to rule, the proposition must run thus: <hi>The word Priest is used fifty times in the Pontifician sense.</hi> And now it is as easily answered, as that Paralo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gisme of the Divel would have been; if he had spoke out the whole sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, which he seemed to quote. And therefore when they conclude, <hi>none but Papists use the word Priest, unless scoffers at Ministers, whom in derision they nick-name Priests:</hi> we must thank them for it, who fall
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121235:14"/>out with the name, and have put this scoffe into the Quakers mouth, who hath most of his weapons out of the Non-conformists shop, as Dr. <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derson</hi> hath evidently discovered in his Preface to his last Edition of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION.</head>
               <p>Pag. 22. §. 2. <hi>It is said in one Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick, that the Collect, Epistle, and Gospel appointed for one Sunday shall serve all the week after. By vertue of this these in Cathedrals were read eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day, albeit they had no Communion. But another Rubrick runs thus, the Collects, Epistles and Gospels to be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed at the celebration of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. So that these two Rubricks fight, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:121235:14"/>
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>ASpirit of contradiction will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect its own image upon any thing: otherwise what contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is there between these two injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, <hi>They shall be read at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,</hi> and, <hi>they shall be read when there is no Communion?</hi> And when they gather from the first, that if they be read when there is no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, it is without warrant: they must needs except Holy days by vertue of the first Rubrick after the Communion, which requires all the service appointed for the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be then read, to the end of the Prayer for the state of Christs Church, though there be no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. So that this Harmony re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sults from both these Rubricks joyn'd together, that they are to be read on all Holy dayes, and on other dayes if there be a Communion, and that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:121235:15"/>on those dayes the same should serve which serv'd on Sunday.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION.</head>
               <p>Pag. 23. § 3. <hi>The Rubrick before the general confession at the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on runs thus, Then shall this confession be made in the name of all those that are to receive the holy Communion either by one of them, or by one of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters. This gives liberty to Lay or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate men to officiate, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>SEeing it is lest at liberty to be made by one of the People or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister, there can be no inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in this except the Minister will. But when they say, that <hi>thus a Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man shares in administring the Lords Supper;</hi> they condemn their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, who sometimes require those, that come for the Sacrament, to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:121235:15"/>make not only a general, but a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular confession both of their sins and experiences.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 23. §. 4. They promise to speak more upon this Paragraph, when they come to the body of the book, and then I shall answer them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION.</head>
               <p>Pag. 23. §. 5. <hi>The Rubrick after the Communion saith, Every Parish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner shal communicate at the least three times in the Year: but in the exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation before the Communion the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster is to say, I bid you all that be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent and beseech you, that you will not refuse to come being so lovingly called and bidden by God himself. Yet the foresaid Rubrick seems to dispense with Gods own invitation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:121235:16"/>
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>GOds invitation calls <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them to come often: but how doth this injunction, <hi>thou shalt come at least thrice a Year,</hi> dispense with it? <hi>Be instant in Prayer,</hi> saith the Apostle: If a father saith to his child, <hi>pray at least when you go to bed or I will whip you;</hi> should this command be thought to dispense with the command of the Apostle, when on the contrary it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acts a measure of obedience to it? I require you to be in a fitting posture and to have an appetite to come of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, saith the Church; but at least come thrice a Year, or you shall be punish'd: here is nothing said, which contradicts her self, or dispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth with the command of God. When they urge the Primitive pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, of communicating at every so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn meeting; I doubt many, who say <hi>Amen</hi> to this Petition, condemn
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:121235:16"/>themselves for not administring once in many Years. They adde, <hi>Why must Easter-day be one, more then any other Lords day; seeing every Lords day is celebrated upon the same ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count,</hi> viz. <hi>in memory of the Resurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our Lord?</hi> Answer, there was a good reason of this custome at the first appointment, that being all met together at once to put on the livery of their Lord, they might with joynt consent openly profess and own before the heathens, that liv'd amongst them, whose retainers they were, which they did severally at other times. Therefore was one day appointed, in which all should communicate. <hi>But why should Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster-day be that high day since every Lords day, &amp;c.</hi> By the same reason they might ask, why is thanks to be returned to God for delivering us from the Gun-powder Treason on the fifth of <hi>November,</hi> since we are every Sunday to give thanks for the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121235:17"/>benefits of Christ, amongst which redemption is one. Easter-day is not onely the Day of the Resurrection, because the first day of the week, as every other Sunday is; but also, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is at the same time of the year, as near as can be calculated. Or if it were not, yet whereas other Sundayes are set apart to comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morate all that Christ did for us; this is set apart more peculiarly in memory of the Resurrection. They proceed, <hi>But where it is added in that Rubrick [he shall also receive the Sacraments and other rites &amp;c.] this is no other, but non-sense or worse. For What Sacraments are there else for a Communicant of the Lords Supper to receive? Is Baptism to be reiterated? are the Popish Sacraments to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called? &amp;c.</hi> Here they are at the juggling mentioned before; leaving out something which would make it sense, namely these words which follow after in the same breath, <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:121235:17"/>to the Order in this Book ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed.</hi> This being supplied is not the sense clear? <hi>Every Parishioner</hi> [that is to be baptized,] <hi>shall be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed,</hi> and <hi>every Parishioner</hi> [that is to receive the Communion] <hi>shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the communion according to the order prescribed in this book.</hi> And he that is to receive any other <hi>rites,</hi> as <hi>confirmation, marriage &amp;c. shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them according to the order ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in this book.</hi> But they use a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Sophistry which makes that which I have discovered, the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to be discern'd: That whereas, <hi>he shall communicate thrice a year,</hi> is one sentence; and <hi>He shall also re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacraments and other rites according to order,</hi> is another sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: they borrow these words <hi>[thrice a year]</hi> from the first sentence, and make them to have influence upon the last. And so all their ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils against this Rubrick fall to the ground.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:121235:18"/>
               <head>OBJECTION.</head>
               <p>Pag. 24. §. 6. <hi>The Rubrick before the Catechism concludeth thus. [And that no man may think, that any detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment shall come to children by defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of their confirmation; he shall know for truth, that it is certain by Gods word, that children being bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed have all things necessary for salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and be undoubtedly saved.] This Rubrick gives them more assurance of salvation, then ever God gives them. For if they be godly or wicked, it makes their salvation certain.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>THe intention of these words is plainly expressed, <hi>viz.</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a scruple, which might arise from deferring of Confirmation till the childe come to years of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, as if the child had not all
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:121235:18"/>the ordinances, that are necessary without it. Now the known ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate intention of the speaker is to bound the sense of his words, if they are capable of bearing an untruth in a larger acceptation. Therefore they can import no more then this, that children baptized have all things necessary to salvation though they die without confirmation, as much as they have after it; and shall be as undoubtedly saved without it, as with it. They have all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary in the kinde of means, and shall be undoubtedly saved, suppos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they live an holy life according to their baptism; for otherwise nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could they be saved, though they were confirmed. And truely charity would put as handsome a construction upon these words, as upon the Apostles, that Baptism saveth; and understand neither the one nor the other of the washing with water alone, without an inward
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:121235:19"/>cleansing, when they are applyed to such as are capable of actual sin and Repentance. So that these words ingenuously interpreted run thus, <hi>If one be baptized, and renounce not his baptism by an unchristian life; he shall undoubtedly be saved, although he should die before the opportunity of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation came:</hi> and when they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with this interrogation of a strong denial, <hi>Is this a truth?</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, yea, and grounded upon the word of God.</p>
               <p>In the 6. Paragraph there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing objected, which concerns the Layman to take notice of, but onely the last words, <hi>That persons are not bound to receive the communion above thrice a year by the Rubrick of the communion; and therefore need not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive on their marriage day, as they are required by the Rubrick after Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony.</hi> Was ever heard such a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence as this? One place saith, thou shalt receive thrice a year; and the other saith, thou shalt receive on
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:121235:19"/>the day of marriage: Doth not this plainly require, that if the 3. times were before, there should be then a fourth; or if they were not before, that this time should [if not make a 4th, yet at least] be one of the three?</p>
               <p>The like cavil they make pag. 25. §. 8. against these words of the Rubr. after the Communion of the sick, in the time of the Plague &amp;c. when none can be gotten to communicate with the sick, for fear of infection, upon special request of the diseased, the minister may communicate with him alone. Against this they except, <hi>that the very nature of the Sacrament requires a publick administration, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause there must be a communion of more then two persons in the receiving of it.</hi> Answer. Why must it be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick? because there must be more then two? may it not be private for all that? Publick and private are not distinguished by the number present, but by the place. Two, as well as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:121235:20"/>three, may do an action in publick; if the place be publick: and ten as well as two, may do it in private; if the place be private. And why must there be more then two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons? doth not our Saviour Christ say, <hi>two or three?</hi> Their first reason is, <hi>because in the Rubrick after the publick communion, it is said, that there shall be no communion except four or three at the least communicate.</hi> But they have found out the answer themselves, that this order con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns only publick not private com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munions. That which they reply to it is nothing; <hi>That it appears not by the word, that there is any warrant or necessity for such communions.</hi> For neither doth the word deny that there may be such necessity; nor doth it prohibit to gratifie, where it is; and a non-prohibition is a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, if it tend to edification; which they do not deny. To shew there is no necessity, they quote the first
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:121235:20"/>communion after the sick, where the Curate is prescribed to instruct the sick man, <hi>that if through any just impediment, as lack of company, he receive not the Sacrament with the mouth; yet supposing he believe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and be thankful, he doth eat and drink the body and blood of Christ profitably to his souls health.</hi> But I answer, that the Rubrick under de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate comes after that last quoted, and is an exception from it. For if the sick person be not satisfied of this, that the Minister saith; though there be no simple necessity, yet there may be a necessity to him: and therefore it is put down, <hi>that it must be done on the sick mans special request.</hi> Besides he may possibly plead, that he hath not an heart <hi>to repent, believe, and be thankful;</hi> but hopes these graces will be quickned by the use of such an operative means. So that there may be a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of it <hi>quoad hominem;</hi> though
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:121235:21"/>it be declared not necessary in it self, upon supposition that a man can <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent &amp;c.</hi> without it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION.</head>
               <p>Pag. 26. § 1. <hi>The first words of the Liturgy are these, At what time soever a sinner doth repent him of his sin from the bottom of his heart I will put all his wickednesse out of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, saith the Lord. This is in the Rubrick before it called a sentence of Scripture and the place alledged is Ezek.</hi> 21.22. <hi>But that text runs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise in the Original and new Translation of the Bible, viz. If the wicked will turn from all his sins which he hath committed and keep all my statutes and do that which is lawful and right he shall surely live and not dye, all the transgressions that he hath committed shall not be mentioned to him. Here is little harmony between the Service-book and Gods book.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:121235:21"/>
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>LEt any unprejudiced Person view the places, and see if there be not as exact an harmony betwixt them, as betwixt a Ministers prayer and the Lords prayer, or his doctrine and his Text. The difference is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Phrase; <hi>Repentance</hi> in one, <hi>and turning from evil and doing of good,</hi> which are the two parts of <hi>Repentance,</hi> in the other: <hi>putting them out of remembrance</hi> in the one, <hi>&amp; not mentioning them</hi> in the other. How then can these Petitioners say that here is no <hi>harmony?</hi> especially when they are wont to tell the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists, that a consequence drawn from Scripture is Scripture; and carelesse auditours, that the Sermons they make according to the word of God, is the word of God. But <hi>the very first words,</hi> they say, <hi>have no war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of them from the text:</hi> which I
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:121235:22"/>deny; because no time being limited, no time is excluded by the text. However no doubt but it hath war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from other places of Scripture, as they themselves in all probability have many times interpreted them; <hi>That it is never too late to return to God from the bottom of the heart.</hi> They add, that it is dissonant from another Scripture, <hi>To day if you will hear his voice &amp;c.</hi> But that Scripture doth not deny, but a man that heareth not to day, shall yet be saved if he hear to morrow: but only implyes how dangerous it is to defer; not least a man should miss of pardon, if he repents sincerely, though lately, but least he should not repent at all, his heart being hardened by continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in sin, or the day of death surprising him in the state of impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, when God will swear in his wrath that he shall not enter into his Rest. The same is clearly the sense of the other Scripture, which they
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:121235:22"/>in vain provoke to fall out with the sentence under consideration. <hi>To day while it is called to day, lest your hearts be hardened through the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulnesse of sin.</hi> They say further. <hi>That these words [at what time so ever] sound, as if a man could repent when he lists; and therefore have no ground in the word of God.</hi> But they might as well say, that those words of Christ are groundlesse too, <hi>whosoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver cometh to me I will in no wise cast him out.</hi> Which <hi>[whosoever]</hi> includ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him that hath stood out all his life long; and therefore by their reasoning implyes, that a man may repent when he lists. They go on, <hi>It is true this is seemingly put off thus, (The book speaks the sense although not the very words of the text.) But this is too frigid an answer to satisfie the objection: for it is said to be a sentence of Scripture, not an exhortation ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to sense only.</hi> But I answer, that the word <hi>sentence,</hi> doth by the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:121235:23"/>etymology and common use of it, appear to signifie rather the sense, then the rigid words of a proposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For sentence comes from <hi>sentio,</hi> and it is usual among exposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours to write, <hi>sententia Pauli,</hi> for the meaning of <hi>Paul;</hi> and <hi>sententia ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borum,</hi> for the meaning of the words. And why may not that Scripture, which containes the same sense, be put down in the Margin of the Common prayer Book; as well as usually it is in the references of the Bible? Especially seeing the Apostles and Christ Jesus do quote Scriptures many times not in the same, but in very divers phrases; and add not onely, <hi>saith the Lord,</hi> but <hi>as it is written.</hi> For that which they urge in the last place, <hi>that it agrees not with the sense, but is contrary to it, therefore it is untrue and injurious to charge the Apostles with the like in alledging the old Testament in the New;</hi> hath been answered with a
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121235:23"/>denyal before, when I shewed that it agrees exactly with the sense of the place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION.</head>
               <p>Pag. 27. 2. <hi>That expression in the Confession</hi> viz. <hi>There is no health in us, is incongruous and improper; because most of the common sort understand not the true mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>HOw oft have I heard this incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous and improper expression used in <hi>extempore</hi> prayers; and yet no exception taken at it? <hi>That there is no soundnesse in us, but wounds, and bruises</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:121235:24"/>
               <head>OBJECTION.</head>
               <p>Pag. 27. 3. <hi>After the first Lesson,</hi> Te Deum, <hi>or</hi> Benedicite, <hi>are to be read before the second Lesson; and so they interrupt the continued reading of the holy Scripture, which the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to that book would bear us in hand is provided against.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>I Shall take notice of this in the next Section, where they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the same interruption by the <hi>Antiphonies</hi> and <hi>Responds.</hi> Their next argument against <hi>Te Deum</hi> is, <hi>that it is in use among the Papists.</hi> But what if it be? Because reformation hath weeded out the Tares, must the wheat be plucked up also? For they have not a word against the truth, goodnesse, or usefulnesse of this Hymn. Touching the Canticle cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:121235:24"/>
                  <hi>Benedicite,</hi> beginning <hi>O all ye works of the Lord,</hi> they have this note. <hi>Whereas the song is said in the Title of it in the Apocrypha to be the song of the three holy children, which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the third of Daniel after this place [And they walked in the fire praysing God.] This is an abusing and belying of the Canonical text in Dan.</hi> 3. <hi>in which there is no hint of any such thing.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>WHen they affirm, <hi>This is a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying &amp;c.</hi> they do not sure mean, that the saying of this song is a belying of the book of Daniel. For when I say the words, I do not say the Title, nor call it <hi>A song of the</hi> 3. <hi>children</hi> &amp;c. If they mean that this title, which is given it in the Apocrypha, doth bely Canonical <hi>Daniel;</hi> that is nothing to us. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, wherein appears the lye? For
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:121235:25"/>he that made this title, possibly might have before him some copy of the book of <hi>Daniel,</hi> into which this song was inserted; and so to him it might be onely a falshood, and not a lye, to say it follows in the third Chapter. But they cannot conclude, that this was not the song of the three children, because, it is not mentioned in <hi>Daniel.</hi> For <hi>Philo Judaeus</hi> relates many passages of <hi>Moses,</hi> which are not down in the Books of <hi>Moses;</hi> and yet <hi>Mr. Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs</hi> makes use of them, writing of Moses his self-denyal.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION.</head>
               <p>§. 4. <hi>The many Antiphonies and Responds have no pattern or warrant in the word of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:121235:25"/>
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>YEs, that they have, For the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels cryed to <hi>to one another</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Holy. And when <hi>Miriam</hi> went forth with the women in the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity to prayse the Lord, <hi>she an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered them</hi> and said, Praise ye the Lord, &amp;c. And when some of <hi>Davids</hi> singers were appointed to use the Cymbal, some the Harp, some the Psaltery, and others the voice; it is not probable that they sung all at once and together. Besides if it were granted, that such a way of singing was not then in use; yet, as they think they keep to the example of the first celebration, though they do not lye at the Lords table but sit, because they keep the Table-posture which is now in use, and may well think themselves excused, though they do not sing the same tunes, which <hi>David</hi> set his Psalms for; so
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:121235:26"/>we by the same reason may follow the pattern of <hi>Davids</hi> singers, though we do not sing the same way but by alternate courses, that way of sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing being in common use now. For though it had no Pattern; yet it hath a warrant for all their denial, because it was not forbidden. For a circumstance of worship, being not forbidden, is confessed by the most rigid non-conformists to be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted; and this can be no more, then a circumstance. And indeed by the same reason whereby they ask a Pattern or warrant in Scripture for singing or praying by turns, yea and by much more reason the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker may demand a pattern or warrant in Scripture for Cuffs &amp; Ribbands, and such like punctilio's, which it were beneath the Authority &amp; Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty of Scripture to take cognizance of. But as I observed before, so this Paragraph forceth me to do it again; that the Quakers do but improve
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:121235:26"/>those indiscrete principles, which wiser men [but such as serve an Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothesis] do assert for their own ends, but cannot endure to have them urged against themselves. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they will not endure, that others should do any thing in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine worship, which they have not a command or example for in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; they themselves will not be tyed in the same bonds, wherewith they oblige others. For when they receive the communion sitting, and at noon, and have no widows in their Churches; this is contrary to example: and when they salute not one another with an holy kiss, nor set apart something for the poor on the first day of the week, nor anoint the sick with oyl; this is contrary to a command. And if that which is contrary to example and precept, be lawful, when the case altereth and the reason ceaseth; much more is that lawful, which onely hath no
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:121235:27"/>precept or pattern, but is opposite to none.</p>
               <p>They next ask <hi>How these things can be done in Faith?</hi> Why not? For to what article of our Creed are they contrary? But if by Faith they understand [in the sense of those words, <hi>what is not of Faith is sin</hi> [a belief that what is done is lawful; then they may be well done in faith, because I have proved them lawful, being no where forbidden. And whereas they say it must be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>will-worship;</hi> I answer, that the will-worship, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> findes fault with, consists not in using such forms of worship, which are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where prescribed in the word, but in placing holinesse in that which is not made holy by a divine instituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but left indifferent; or in place<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unholinesse in that which is not made unholy by a divine prohibition but left indifferent, as those did who were subject to ordinances, <hi>Touch
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:121235:27"/>not, tast not, handle not,</hi> of whom the Apostle speaks in that place <hi>Col.</hi> 2. &amp; if so; I doubt the accusers are more guilty of this fault then the accused. For the <hi>accused,</hi> who are rightly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, place not any intrinsecal ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness in these Responds, but use them only because they judge them incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of devotion, or because they are prescribed by them whose Office it is in publick administrations to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine what is most conducible to edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. But the <hi>accusers</hi> place an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holinesse in them, and say <hi>Respond not, cross not, kneel not;</hi> which is pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel to, <hi>Touch not, tast not, handle not,</hi> the genuine voice of the will-worshipper. They are upon it again, that these Responds are to be excepted against, <hi>they are so fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in the Mass-book.</hi> But 1. Those who compiled this Liturgy, had as great an Antipathy to the Mass<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>book [though more wisely modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted] as these Petitioners can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to. For several of them opposed
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:121235:28"/>it to the blood. 2. Such reasonings as these, <hi>It is in the Mass-book,</hi> ergo <hi>not to be endured;</hi> are the greatest commendations of the Mass-book. For when we fall out with it, for that in it, which is lawful, we give the adversary an handsome occasion to think, that we are as unreasonable, when we condemn that in it which is unlawful. A wrestler must get in to him, that he would overthrow: And we must come as neer in our concessions, as truth will give leave, to those that we would confute. They lastly argue from the preface to the book of Common Prayer, which saith, <hi>that the reading of the holy Scripture is therein so set forth, that all things shall be done in order, without breaking one piece thereof from another, and for this cause be cut off Antiphonies, Responds, Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatories, and such like things as did break the continual course of reading the Scriptures.</hi> But it is clear to him
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:121235:28"/>that will read the Preface, that the composers aimed onely at such an interruption, as was in use before, when a book of Scripture was often begun to be read, but never read. For so they expresse themselves in the former part of the Preface, and in the words immediatly preceding mention is made of the Calendar, as a remedy of that interruption they intend. So that the Preface finds fault onely with such an interrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as is inconsistent, not with such an one as stands with the ends of the Calendar, that so much of the Bible should be read over once a year. Now notwithstanding that interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the Antiphonies &amp;c. which the Petitioners plead against; more of the Bible will be read every year according to the rule of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer-Book, then there would by following the appointment of the Directory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:121235:29"/>
               <head>OBJECTION.</head>
               <p>Pag. 28.5. <hi>If the Litany must be read, why must the praying part be performed so much by the people? &amp;c. There is no ground for this in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; yet we must be made to believe, that there is nothing in the Liturgy but what is evidently grounded upon the word.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>IF any would see the expediency of these things; others have written on it. My designe is onely to shew their lawfulnesse: for if they are lawful, a Christian <hi>may</hi> use them with a safe conscience; yea <hi>must,</hi> when he is enjoyned by those whose office it is to discourse of the expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of them in a convocation. That belongs not to a private man, but to pray God to direct the officers of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:121235:29"/>the Church, and onely to inform his own conscience concerning the lawfulnesse of that which they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe. This being premised, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude contradictorily to that asserti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theirs, That there is no ground in Scripture for such a way of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. For that is evidently grounded upon the word, which is prescribed by lawful authority, and is no where forbidden in the word, as this kind of praying under question is not. They next ask, wherefore that clause in the Litany [From the Tyranny of the Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> and all his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testable enormities] is left out? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, To obey is better then sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; and to submit to the use of a more defective Liturgy lawfully commanded, is better then to use a more compleat one in disobedience. I shall not therefore inquire, why this petition is left out; but charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly believe no less then dutifully, that there was a reason, and for ought I
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:121235:30"/>know this might be it. That this Litany being appointed for a stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing form of Prayer, ought to contain no Petitions but such as are seaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable at all times. Now who knows how soon the Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> may lay aside his Tyranny and his detestable enormities, upon which this Petition would soon grow out of date. That which concludes this Section, and is the whole of the next, hath been answered already; insisting onely upon alterations made in this book from that, which was in use in K. <hi>Edwards</hi> time.</p>
               <p>The 29. Pag. §. 7. Begins with the same objection concerning the corrupt Translations, which was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered before, and is of force in a measure, though not so great, against the Translation of K. <hi>James.</hi> They next insist upon that, which they had mentioned before, the answer where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I deferred till this Section. Their
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:121235:30"/>words are these, <hi>It is too too palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that in the Prayers and proper pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faces for Christmas day and Whitsun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, there are some things not onely uncertain, bat false, yea impossible to be true; and therefore not evidently grounded on the word of God. In the Collect for Christmas day, and seven dayes after, we must say to God, that he hath given Christ this day to be born &amp;c. On what Scripture is this evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently grounded, that he was born that very day,</hi> viz. <hi>December</hi> 25? I answer, when a Minister in his <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempore</hi> Prayer on the 5. of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> hath these words or the like, <hi>Thou, who this day didst deliver us;</hi> on what Scripture is this evidently grounded, that the deliverance was given on that very day? and yet the thanksgiving it self is grounded on the word of God. I wonder, that wise men should thus wish to dye with the <hi>Philistines,</hi> and pull down the 25. of <hi>December</hi> on the head of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:121235:31"/>the 5. of <hi>November.</hi> For I suppose they are as willing to keep that day and put up that thanksgiving, as others. But they come with a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reserve, <hi>If it did appear so, viz.</hi> that Christ was born on the 25. of <hi>December.] how can we say the same without gross lying to God seven other dayes more; seeing he was born but once, and on one day only?</hi> Answer, Let it be according to their minde, that Christ was not born on the 7. dayes after, nor yet on that day it self, taking the words in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per sense; yet it can be no lie to say, he was born on that day, in such a sense, as is here known to be meant. For words, that signifie one thing in propriety of Language, do signifie not only a divers, but a clean con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary thing, in another sense; and if that sense be notorious, it is no lye. Doubtless he is a God, saith <hi>Elijah</hi> of <hi>Baal.</hi> He told no lie, because all knew his meaning, that he was no
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:121235:31"/>God. But to bring this nearer to our purpose, might not the Jews, when they kept the Feast of Pass<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, say to God; we thank thee for saving us this day from the destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Angel: and yet the Passover in probability would not fall out on the same day of the moneth in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years? By the same reason, though Christ was not born on the 25. of <hi>December,</hi> yet it may be said then, <hi>we thank thee for the birth of Christ on this day:</hi> the meaning being notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously known to be this, <hi>for the birth of thy son on that day, for the comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration of which this day is hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or set apart.</hi> So then it being no lye on Christmas-day, though Christ should have been born on any other day of the moneth; neither can it be a lye on the 7. dayes following. For to perfect this answer in the words of <hi>Mr. Sparrow</hi> in his <hi>Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onale;</hi> It's manifest, that the Church doth not use the word <hi>Day</hi> for a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:121235:32"/>day of 24. hours, but in the usual acceptation of it in holy Scripture, where by the word <hi>day</hi> is signified the whole time designed to one and the same purpose, though it last several natural dayes. Thus all the time, which God appoints to the reclaiming of a sinner by merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful chastisements or threatnings, is termed the day of their visitation. He gives other instances, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes; In like manner all that time, which is appointed by the Church for the thankful commemoration of the same grand blessing, for the so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity of one and the same feast, is as properly called a day, and all that time it may be said dayly, <hi>to day while it is called to day,</hi> as well as all our life, St. <hi>Paul</hi> saith, it is called, <hi>Hodiè,</hi> to day. You see then, how little cause they have to bestow such soul language upon this part of the Liturgy; calling it <hi>a lying to God, &amp; an horrible abusing of God.</hi> But God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:121235:32"/>that any son of the Church of <hi>England</hi> should be so ill bred, as to give them reviling for reviling.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION.</head>
               <p>Pag. 29. §. 8. <hi>After the proper Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faces at the Communion follows this, Therefore with Angels and Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angels &amp;c. Here is another uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to say nothing of the untruth of it, for the Scripture never speaks of more Archangels then one.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p n="1">(1.) WEre the pretended un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty granted; yet are not more uncertain things then this, usually uttered in <hi>extempore</hi> prayers? (2.) This Hymn doth not say, there are Archangels: but onely, taking it as probable, saith we with them do magnifie God; and such a concent with them, upon supposition
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:121235:33"/>they are, is certainly grounded on the word of God. (3.) Archangel signifies no more then a chief Angel: now, if there be the least degree of superiority betwixt Cherubim and Seraphim, there are chief Angels. And that distinction of Thrones, Dominions, Principalities, Powers, will infer so much, if it be not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained to earthly dignities, as it seems by the context it ought not, Col. 1.16. <hi>That are in heaven, and that are in Earth, visible and invisible, whether they be thrones &amp;c.</hi> (4.) If that, which the Petitioners do here confidently assert, be true, that Christ is an Archangel; then it is manifest, that there are two Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angels at the least. For we read of another Archangel besides him. 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 5. where it is said, that <hi>Christ shall descend with the voyce of an Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angel and the sound of the Trumpet.</hi> Now then except this voice of an Archangel be the voice of Christ
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:121235:33"/>[and then it were a strange expre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssion at the first sight] it is plainly asserted in this place, that there is another beside him. Indeed our Translation reads it, <hi>the Archangel,</hi> as if there were but one: but seeing the Article <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is not prefixt; it is to be rendered <hi>an Archangel,</hi> unlesse it were otherwise known, that there are no more then one, which is not known but is under enquiry. But to put all out of doubt, we read of an Archangel besides Christ in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle of <hi>Jude,</hi> even <hi>Michael,</hi> who strove with the Devil about the body of <hi>Moses.</hi> There is no way to evade this, but by saying that Christ was an Angel before his coming in Flesh, I mean not in respect of nature, but of title, as the word signifies an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, but that could not be, for his incarnation was the first step of his minoration: till then he was only in the form of God, whereas in this title he is in the form of a servant,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:121235:34"/>since they are all ministring spirits. Besides it's said, he <hi>durst</hi> not bring against the Devil a railing accusati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which is a term too low for him, who is God blessed for ever, to say he <hi>dares</hi> not sin. And lastly, he said to the Devil, <hi>The Lord rebuke thee:</hi> whereas, if it had been the Son of God before the state of humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oh, he would have said, <hi>I the Lord rebuke thee..</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION.</head>
               <p>Pag. 30. §. 9 <hi>In one of the prayers after the Communion, it is prayed that those things, which for our unworthynesse we dare not, and for our blindnesse we cannot ask; vouchsafe to give us &amp;c. This is a contradiction, for while we say we dare not ask, we doe ask.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:121235:34"/>
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>IF figurative speeches be taken properly; no marvail though there be found contradictions, or non-sense in them all. Now here is clearly a Rhetorical figure in this prayer, and its called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or, <hi>Praeteritio, ubi quaedam simulatè dicuntur praeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitti quae tamen disertè memorantur,</hi> when some things are feigned to be past over, which yet are eloquently exprest. There are many examples of it in common speech, and in the best Authors, both humane and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine. <hi>Cic. pro Pomp. Sinite hoc loce, Quirites, praeterire me nostram calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem, quae tanta fuit, ut eam ad au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res L. Luculli non è praelio nuncius, sed ex sermone Rumor afferret.</hi> i. e. I will say nothing, O Romans, by your leave, of our overthrow, which was so great, that it was brought to the ears of L. <hi>Lucullus,</hi> not by a
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:121235:35"/>messenger out of the battle, but by a rumour arising out of the common talk. The Orator saith, he would not mention that overthrow, which yet he expresseth with the greatest significancy imaginable; so great, that none were left to bring the General himself the news, till the common rumour first informed him. You see then an example in the best of prophane writers, who sometimes saith he will speak nothing of a sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, which he bestows whole pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges upon. You shall see the same in the best of divine Authors. For when our Saviour saith to his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, <hi>I do not say that I will pray to the Father for you;</hi> Dr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> and others, no good friends to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer, do gather from those words a strong promise, that he <hi>would</hi> pray the father for them. By the same reason the Petitioners might say, there is a contradiction in his words. Besides there are degrees
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:121235:35"/>of daring, and not daring; so that they may both consist together <hi>in graduremisso:</hi> For Hope and Fear, though of a most advers nature, yet are like a Prisoner and the Souldier that keeps him, tied together in one chain, saith <hi>Seneca.</hi> So then that phrase signifies no more then this: we beg of thee those great mercies, which are so stupendously great, we cannot ask them without fear and trembling. It is but such a strain of Devotion as that of the Publican, who would not lift up his eyes to heaven, and yet did in that sense wherein <hi>David</hi> saith, <hi>I will lift up my eyes to the hills &amp;c.</hi> Or like that of <hi>Ezra,</hi> who saith, <hi>I am ashamed to lift vp my face to thee for our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are gone over our heads;</hi> and yet he did it while he was ashamed to do it. <hi>David</hi> also saith, <hi>my iniquities have taken hold on me, so that I am not able to look up;</hi> and yet he looks up with an eye of expectation in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:121235:36"/>next words. So that there is no contradiction; if the sentence broke off, where they break it off. But the book goes on thus, <hi>Vouchsafe to give vs for the worthinesse of Christ.</hi> Now as the Apostle saith, that at the same time, he was both weak and strong; weak in himself and strong in Christ: so at the same time we may be bold to ask, and be not bold to ask; not bold by reason of our unworthyness, and yet bold by reason of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynesse of Christ, which two dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent respects are expressed in the Prayer. Indeed the Petitioners take notice of this answer, <hi>but then bid us take this reply. If our own unworthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse causeth us not to dare to ask; why do we pray else where for ought else at all?</hi> But this is no reply, but onely a repeating of that which hath been already answered; and shall be now again with the same answer, That we do else where pray for ought else, because though our unworthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:121235:36"/>causeth us not to dare to ask, yet the consideration of Christs wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynesse supervenes and gives us boldnesse, by which we ask some things in particular, and all things in general.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION.</head>
               <p>Pag. 30.10. <hi>In the second prayer at publick baptisme we pray that Infants coming to baptism may receive remissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of sins by spiritual regeneration. How can this be?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>HOw can that be, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> saith to the same purpose, that God according to his mercy saveth us by the washing of water and the renewing of the holy Ghost? What is salvation, but saving us from sin chiefly? and wherein consists that but in remission of sin partly? So that when the Apostle saith, sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:121235:37"/>is received by regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; These Petitioners say, no, one piece of salvation is not. Mark next how they argue, <hi>Remission of sin is not received by spiritual Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but by and from the blood of Christ.</hi> Is there any thing in this Argument, but only <hi>Petitio Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pii?</hi> For if there be, it must lye in a supposition, that if it be by Christs blood, it cannot be by regeneration, and consequently that these two are opposite and not subordinate; and they might as well say, the bread is not cut by the knife, but by the hand. What though <hi>without shedding of blood there is no remission?</hi> must it therefore be false, <hi>that without ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness no man can see God?</hi> Both are requisite, <hi>The blood of Christ clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth from all sin:</hi> but it's through the washing of water and renewing of the holy Ghost. How rashly then do they conclude, that except we away with this expression; we are
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:121235:37"/>more for mans falshood, then Gods truth.</p>
               <p>§ 11. They object against an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer in the Catechism, which is dubious and may be ill interpreted. But since they charge no deeplier, I shall save my reply. For in doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful sayings the best sense should be taken; and no Catechism or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of faith can be put down in such clear tearms, but some, say they, can subscribe it, if they have liberty to take it in their own sense, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out revoking any opinion of their own. They object against another answer of the Catechism thus, <hi>where it is demanded</hi> [<hi>why are Infants bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed when by reason of their tender age they cannot perform them,</hi> i. e. <hi>Faith and Repentance?</hi>] <hi>The answer is this, [Yea they do perform them by their sureties] which is a meer tale. For however the sureties promise these in behalf of the Infant; yet it was never read nor heard of in Scripture, that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:121235:38"/>one man Repented or believed in the name or room of another.</hi> Answer, The Infant may be said to perform them so far, as he is capable of it; and no more is required. Certainly, when these Petitioners deal with the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists, they will argue otherwise; granting that faith &amp; Repentance are required to baptism, and yet not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying that children are to be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed: both which could not consist, except they had these graces vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, though not formally. And where as they urge, <hi>that many sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties themselves are not true believers;</hi> I answer, no more are many adult persons, who yet are to be baptized, if they are professed believers; and this sentence that Infants perform the conditions by their sureties, can bear no other sense, but that they professedly perform them, or rather a profession of faith and repentance is a real performance of the requisites in the person to be baptized. So that a
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:121235:38"/>considering man will see nothing in this cavil, but what may become an Anabaptist, &amp; makes as much against the Directory as the Liturgy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION.</head>
               <p>Pag. 31. § 12. Speaking of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination they have these words, <hi>To which all the people are required to say Amen; whereby many of them are necessitated to curse themselves.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p n="1">(1.) EVery man ought to wish in general, that all final impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent sinners may be cursed. For else he hath not an heart according to Gods heart, and delighteth not in that righteousnesse, wherewith God judgeth the world. Indeed we ought, as God doth, to will all men to be saved; if they accept of Gods gracious tearmes: If not, we are to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:121235:39"/>will their damnation. But (2.) The sentences themselves have not the form of a curse, but onely of an as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sertion; being indicative, not opta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive: not <hi>cursed be;</hi> but, <hi>cursed is</hi> such an one. And whereas they stick upon the <hi>Amen,</hi> as if in that word the people wished those evils to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; it cannot be. For if, <hi>Amen,</hi> be joyned to a wish; it consents, and saith, <hi>so be it:</hi> But if it be annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed only to an affirmation; it doth no more then assent, and say <hi>it is so.</hi> Yea this last is the first sense of the word; since it properly signifies <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily,</hi> or <hi>truely.</hi> But what should I spend words about this frivolous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, when (3.) It would have been of as much force against this cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome among the Jews, as it is against this custom among us. For though the Petitioners shew several diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences between these two, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of place and persons; yet such differences cannot make the Act
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:121235:39"/>lawful to them, and unlawful to us. For what though it was done then in a Mount? why is it not as lawful in the Church? may a man curse him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in a mountain and not in a vally? And what though it was pronounced then by the people? Why may not the people as well hear it from a Minister, and say <hi>Amen</hi> to it? They seem to fetch an Argument from the duty of <hi>Aaron</hi> and his sons, which they say was <hi>at all publick assemblies of the congregation for worship to bless the congregation.</hi> But (1.) the place they quote for it, <hi>Num.</hi> 6.23. &amp;c. mentions not any such thing, as that it should be their <hi>constant</hi> duty in <hi>all</hi> assemblies of the congregation. (2.) The formes of blessing put down in that place signifie no more; then those prayers, which the Minister puts up with and for the people in the very office of the commination. (3.) After he hath cursed [or rather pronounced cursed] all final impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents;
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:121235:40"/>he may when he hath done, bless the particular persons there present, not being able to know that any of them are such. So that there is no contradiction betwixt this office of a Minister and the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of <hi>Aaron</hi> and his sons. They go on, <hi>For Ministers of the Gospel then, whose Office it is to be messengers of Peace, to be employed and that often in cursing the people, as a part of his Office and of publick worship; is such an humane, &amp; unchristian-like inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as hath no warrant from the word of God.</hi> Answer, Was not Christ the messenger of peace? and yet we finde him on a suddain leaping from <hi>Gerizim</hi> to <hi>Ebal,</hi> changing his dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect in the compasse of a verse from blessing to cursing, from <hi>Blessed are ye that mourn,</hi> to, <hi>Wo be to you that laugh now,</hi> which sentence hath more of the form of a curse, then the sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences objected against, as hath been shown. And lest they should pick
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:121235:40"/>out any prerogative in the person of Christ, which might be pretended to alter the case, it is usual in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, <hi>Judgement without mercy to him, that shewes no mercy. Tribulation, anguish &amp;c. to every soule of man that doth evil. If any man love not the Lord Jesus Christ, let him be Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, Maranatha.</hi> But sometimes <hi>Argumentum ad hominem</hi> is more forcible, then ten <hi>Argumenta ad rem.</hi> Therefore let the Pititioners remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that <hi>Curse ye Merosh,</hi> hath been retained in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> where was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Common Prayer</hi> in the <hi>Pew,</hi> nor <hi>Priest</hi> in the <hi>Living.</hi> Indeed in the Parenthesis of that clause, which is now opposed, they grant, that a Minister may curse <hi>this or that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular offender, being according to Christs ordinance convicted, and still remaining refractory and impenitent.</hi> To which I reply, much more may such an one described onely in the general be cursed. For no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:121235:41"/>Person is capable of the curse, but upon account of that general quality, to which the curse is due primarily of it self. If therefore <hi>Thomas</hi> may be cursed, because he is an obstinate sinner, although possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly he may repent; much more may all obstinate sinners in general be cursed, upon condition that they are finally obstinate, which is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood in the commination. Besides the sentence of the Church may erre; and think <hi>Thomas</hi> is guilty, when he is not: But the spirit of God cannot erre, which pronounceth every final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impenitent sinner accursed; nor can the Minister erre, when he saith the same general words without ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of them to any individual. They conclude this point thus, <hi>The commination it self saith, that the Discipline was to put notorious sinners to open Penance in Lent; and that in stead thereof, till the same discipline may be restored, it is thought good to
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:121235:41"/>use this; which shewes plainly, that this is no other then a later spawn of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ.</hi> Answer, Where lies the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick of this inference? Is it in the word <hi>Later?</hi> If so; then to make it good, whatsoever is <hi>later</hi> must be granted <hi>Antichristian:</hi> and then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of themselves have confessed Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elders to be Antichristian, which I would be loth to do. Is it in this, that the commination comes in the room of that Discipline? If so; then it is Antichristian, either because that discipline was <hi>bad</hi> and this sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth the place of it. But what hurt can there be in putting notorious sinners to open penance in Lent? Or else it is Antichristian, because that discipline was <hi>good,</hi> and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, which is substituted, is not <hi>so good.</hi> That is confessed in the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy: But the using of a less good, till the greater can be procured; is no more Antichristianism, then going up the stairs step by step is falling down headlong.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:121235:42"/>
               <p> They end their exceptions against the Liturgy thus, <hi>More might be said of sundry other particulars in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice-book: but we suppose that he that shall duely weigh that which hath been already noted, will think these enough.</hi> And I conclude my vindication in like manner, more might be said in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to every objection: But he, that will duly weigh what hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready noted, will think such a pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual answer to such weak cavils, to be more then enough. Were it not that the inconsiderate vulgar are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with the least shew of a reason, as we see in the Quakers Proselytes; I should accuse my self for this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digality of time and labour, though I owed to God an account of neither.</p>
               <p>The next head, of Rites and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, would fall under my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent designe, the common people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing actors in many of them; but that the Petitioners have saved me that Labour by their ingenuous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:121235:42"/>pag. 36. in these words. <hi>We taking it for granted, that they are in themselves <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or things indifferent; do humbly pray it may be considered, that being such they ought not to be imposed on those, who cannot be fully perswaded in their own minds, that they are lawfull.</hi> This concession being all I aime at, I will not contend for that which is freely granted.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>